🛘 🗗 +39 346 97 32 586 | 🔀 giovanni.pagliarini@aol.com | 🏕 giopaglia.github.io | 🛅 giovanni-pagliarini | 🖫 Giovanni Pagliarini

## Briefly\_

I have cultivated the passion for computer science since the age of 5. I have a training as a computer scientist acquired between universities in Italy, Sweden and Singapore. During my PhD, I am specializing in *Machine Learning*, participating to different projects, and acquiring a more comprehensive approach to design thinking. Recently, to give a broader sense to my profession, I have been approaching the world of green entrepreneurship.

### **Education**

### **PhD in Computer Science and Mathematics**

University of Parma, Italy

· Topics: machine learning, computer vision, time series classification, data science, efficient and parallel computing

11/2020 - Present

08/2018 - 06/2020

09/2015 - 07/2018

- My main research line aims at the formalization of modal symbolic learning, a novel methodology for obtaining *interpretable* intelligent models for computer vision and spatial/temporal pattern recognition
- I'm working on various projects for testing the effectiveness of new machine learning methods: COVID-19 diagnosis from cough/breath sounds; EEG signal interpretation; gas turbine trip prevention; land cover classification from satellite imagery; speech recognition

#### **Master Degree in Computer Science**

University of Gothenburg, Sweden

ECTS: 120, GRADE: G
TOPICS: machine learning, computer vision, bioinformatics, discrete optimization, logic, compilers

- THESIS: Interactionwise Semantic Awareness for Visual Relationship Detection
- I enrolled into an student exchange program (6 months), which took me to the *National University of Singapore (NUS)*, where I deepened my knowledge on computer vision

#### **Bachelor Degree in Computer Science**

University of Ferrara, Italy

- ECTS: 180, Grade: 110/110 with honors
- · Topics: algorithms, computability and complexity theory, parallel computing, computer architecture, operating systems
- THESIS: Optimization of Lattice Boltzmann simulations for Intel Xeon Phi 'Knights Landing'

# **Experience**

**Teaching Assistant** 

Freelance Consultant Ferrara, Italy

• I am doing consulting, mostly on Artificial Intelligence topics

• I program some web scraping utilities and build datasets for research projects

### **Machine Learning Developer**

Gothenburg, Sweden

01/2021 - Present

01/2020 - 06/2020

I tackled a problem of detection of interactions between objects in digital images (Visual Relationship Detection)

I made extensive use of machine learning techniques for computer vision and natural language processing (NLP)

Timade extensive use of machine learning teeriniques for computer vision and natural tanguage processing

Ferrara, Italy & Gothenburg, Sweden

• I held excercise sessions, prepared exercise documents, and graded home assignments

01/2020 - Present

• Courses: Algorithms I, Computability and Complexity, LaTeX Advanced

**Research Trainee**University of Ferrara, Italy

• I optimized a C code for fluid dynamics simulations, targeting highly-parallel architectures

09/2017 - 06/2018

• I measured performance of different data layouts and memory access patterns

 IT Technician
 Ferrara, Italy

 Mercato delle Terre Estensi
 01/2016 - 08/2018

• I built a website and a management/billing system in HTML, PHP, CSS and Javascript

# Technical skills

Machine learning pytorch, computer vision, natural language processing

OS & task automation Linux programming, UNIX shell, data processing & cleaning

**Functional** Haskell, *Julia* **Object-oriented** C++, Java, Python

**Low-level** C (parallel computing with MPI, OpenMP, pthread, CUDA), LLVM

Other LaTeX, TikZ, MySQL, PHP, Javascript, Web scraping, REST APIs, Matlab, R, Go, linear programming

# **Relevant projects**

Sole.jl – Third Millennium Symbolic Learning in Julia 🖸

The first framework for symbolic/interpretabile machine learning and modeling. Accepted at JuliaCon2023.

ModalDecisionTrees.jl - Novel Decision Trees in Julia 🖸 🛗

Interpretable classification of data with dimensional components, such as audio recordings, images, videos, and EEG signals. Presented at JuliaCon2022.

Transparent COVID-19 diagnosis from audio samples of breath and cough 🖺

Modal decision trees allow the extraction of knowledge in explicit form, able to explain the relation between vocal patterns in cough/breath samples and the presence of COVID-19 in a human subject.

Pitòn - Rule extraction from MySQL databases 🖸

Laravel Package (PHP) for training rule-based classification models from data stored in MySQL databases.

Class Semantic Awareness for neural networks

Attempt at improving the standard softmax-based classification framework for neural networks.

Dimensionality reduction: a performance comparison of PCA, LDA and FJLT 🖸 🖺

EasyG – Classifying Electrocardiograms using deep learning 🖸 🖺

University of Ferrara

2022

University of Ferrara

2021

University of Ferrara

2020

University of Ferrara

University of Gothenburg

National University of Singapore

University of Gothenburg

2019

### **Honors & awards**

Member, it-ER Ambassador network

Winner, Acceleration Programme @ MAGICA Summer School 2022

Participant, JuliaCon - Official Julia conference (online edition)

Participant, Technological Contest @ 37th Italian Conference on Computational Logic (CILC)

2021 Finalist, Huawei Italy University Challenge

Participant, Talents for Open Innovation

TV & news appearance, Focus on a research work I conducted on TV program "Oggi è un Altro Giorno"

## Languages

Italian Native speaker

**English** IELTS Academic score: 7.0

## **Personal interests**

Touch typing, ergonomics, codes, languages

Music Arrangement, Professional studies of jazz guitar and piano

**Entertainment** Video-editing, improv Climbing, table tennis Sport

### **Personal Data**

In compliance with the GDPR and Italian Legislative Decree no. 196 dated 30/06/2003, I hereby authorize the recipient of this document to use and process my personal details for the purpose of recruiting and selecting staff and I confirm to be informed of my rights in accordance to art. 7 of the above mentioned decree.